Welcome to deep reinforcement learning
or CSQ24R.
Uh uh really excited to be teaching it
again this quarter. My name is Chelsea.
I am the instructor of the course. I'm
an assistant professor here at Stamford.
I do research on uh reinforcement
learning, robotics, uh and language
models and a variety of other topics. So
the plan for today, so we're going to be
covering uh the course goals and some
logistics. And hopefully this will be
fairly short uh because all this
information is available online. Uh
after that we'll be talking about why
study deep reinforcement learning and
actually get into some technical content
on modeling behavior and reinforcement
learning. Um the key learning goals for
today is what even is deep reinforcement
learning? Uh how do we go about actually
representing behavior in a way that we
can optimize behavior and how do we
formulate a reinforcement learning
problem.
So what do we mean by deep reinforcement
learning? So uh first for reinforcement
learning we mean decision-m problems and
these are problems where a system needs
to make multiple decisions based on a
stream of information. So it'll observe
and then take an action based on that
observation and then observe again and
take another action.
And we'll be studying those kinds of
problems as well as the solutions to
those kinds of problems. And that
includes things like imitation learning,
model free and model based reinforcement
learning, offline and online
reinforcement learning, multitask and
meta reinforcement learning, as well as
uh a little bit of a um extra focus on
reinforcement learning for large
language models and reinforcement
learning for robots. Um, so that's kind
of the crux of the reinforcement
learning aspect of the course and we'll
be emphasizing solutions that scale to
deep neural networks and we'll be
spending a lot less time on solutions
that don't pertain to deep neural
networks.
Now, how does deepl differ from other
machine learning topics? So um
hopefully a lot of you have some
experience with machine learning and
often times in machine learning you'll
have uh some kind of input output pair
XY and you'll have a bunch of these in
some data set and then your goal is to
learn something that can map from X to
Y. Uh and another thing is that we kind
of typically assume in these data sets
is that these data points are sampled
from some distribution and are sampled
um in an independent and identical uh
way from that distribution.
Uh and this is actually where
reinforcement learning differs quite a
bit. So in supervised learning, we have
labeled data. We learn this function.
We're directly told what to output.
we're kind of pulled what the answer is
uh that for that given input and the
inputs are are IID sampled. Now uh in
reinforcement learning the picture is a
little bit different. So ultimately our
goal is to learn behavior uh and we'll
actually use different uh kind of
notations to refer to inputs and
outputs. So specifically our goal will
be to map uh from states to actions and
we'll refer to the function that we do
that mapping as pi.
And unlike in supervised learning we're
not going to be directly told what the
answer is. Our goal will actually be to
learn this behavior from much more
indirect feedback.
And so in reinforcement learning the
goal is to learn this behavior uh pi of
a given s. And this will be from
experience uh and actually experience
often drawn from the policy that you're
learning or or this function that you're
learning.
And the data is not going to be sampled
from a single distribution. It's
actually going to be sampled uh in a way
that actually depends on the policy or
or the function that you're currently
learning. Um so these are the two big
differences. And what I mean by behavior
is this could include motor control like
controlling a robot. It could include a
chatbot that is interacting with a
person. It could be playing a game. It
could be driving a car. It could be an
agent that's interacting with the web.
Uh, and a wide range of other domains.
So, that's how reinforcement learning
differs from typical machine learning.
We don't have the ability to cover
everything in deep reinforcement
learning. And so we're going to try to
focus on the core concept behind heap
reinforcement learning methods so that
you can then use those core concepts to
understand more advanced methods uh
should you choose to dive deeper into
the topic. uh we'll also focus on
implementation of algorithms to get to
the point where you're feel comfortable
implementing algorithms yourself and
we'll give examples in robotics control
and language models uh especially in
lecture and in projects but a lot of the
techniques will generalize more broadly
um and also just a focus on topics that
we think are the most useful and the
most exciting to cover
um if you're interested in more theory
uh and other applications that are kind
of beyond some of these uh CS23 34 can
also be an excellent point.
Um yeah and then the core goal is really
to be able to understand and implement
existing and emerging methods in D
reinforcement.
Cool. So why study D reinforcement
learnings?
Um I'll list out a number of things here
and then we'll dive into each one a
little bit more. Uh so one we already
talked about is going beyond supervised
example and there's a lot of scenarios
where AI model predictions have
consequences.
uh and if we want to take into account
those consequences then we need a
framework for thinking about those
consequences and how to optimize the
behavior with respect to those
consequences. So for example uh if you
like listen to music on Spotify for
example and the Spotify algorithm is
recommending a song for you to play that
recommendation uh or even actually just
playing it directly for you that
recommendation has consequences such
that the next time it recommends a song
it probably shouldn't recommend the same
song or and it might want to also stay
within the same genre and so forth. And
so if we want to think about developing
AI systems that can take into account
those consequences that's what deep
reinforcement learning allows us to do.
Um there's also scenarios where direct
supervision isn't available. Uh so for
example, if you have uh a coding
assistant like uh like cursor or copilot
and you want to give it feedback uh
saying like that was a great uh that did
a great job there or did a poor job
there. Um that supervision is not the
output. Uh it's a more indirect
supervision. Uh and that kind of
learning from that sort of indirect uh
supervision or really any sort of
objective um can be formulated as a
reinforcement learning problem. But it's
a lot more flexible than supervised
learning.
U reinforcement learning is also widely
used and deployed in a number of
performant AI systems. Um
also learning from experience in my
opinion seems kind of fundamental to
intelligence. And so just from a kind of
a philosophical level in terms of
building intelligent machines, uh
figuring out how to actually develop
algorithms that can learn from their own
experience uh seems pretty fundamental
to that. And it's fundamental to be able
to actually make discoveries of new
things rather than just mimicking the
data.
And then lastly, there's also some
pretty exciting uh open research
problems as well. And so it makes it a
pretty exciting area to do research on.
Um, and then lastly, I I was also
actually uh last weekend I was telling a
friend that I was making slides on why
study deep reinforcement learning um and
how I was out of making several slides
on it. And they were like, well, why do
you uh this this question doesn't seem
very hard. Uh the answer is just 1
million in in total compensation from
open AI. Uh so maybe if you're not
motivated by one through four, uh this
can be some motivation.
Okay. Um so diving into beyond
supervised learning uh decision-m
problems are everywhere uh and can't be
directly formulated supervised learning
any sort of AI agent is captured by this
uh also if you want your AI system to
interact with people like chat bots or
recommenders um or scenarios where it
will affect decisions will affect future
outcomes or observations these kind of
feedback loops um these are
reinforcement learning problems um and
then yeah like I mentioned before if
your labels if you don't have labels and
your objective isn't just accuracy or
it's non-ifferiable. These are scenarios
where reinforcement learning is useful.
Um, now I mentioned that that DRL is
used in a variety of different
performance systems. What am I talking
about there? Two examples of legged
robots that have learned behavior with
reinforcement learning. In this case,
reinforcement learning in simulation and
then transferred to the real world. And
so you can get some cool stuff like uh
puffy robots and dancing humanoids. Uh,
and these are actually like real robots
in the real world. uh policies that are
are were trained with deep reinforcement
learning.
Uh beyond legged robots uh and dancing,
you could also get robots that can
manipulate with arms to do tasks uh
using uh in this case imitation learning
uh but still within the scope of this
course. Uh so the left is a robot that
is unloading laundry and folding the
laundry. On the right is a robot that
can fold uh some simple origami. Uh so
some pretty cool stuff you can do with
um with these kinds of methods.
Um you can also learn to play complex
games. So uh several years ago, Deep
Mind used deep reinforcement learning to
train a system to play the game of Go.
And it actually defeated the um the
champion of Go. It defeated Lisa Dole.
Uh which was really impressive in its
own right. And another really cool thing
about it was kind of coming back to this
discovery talon of AI systems. Um there
was this move that surprised everyone
that was an expert in Go. Uh it was
called move 37. Uh and it kind of
discovered a strategy that humans
previously hadn't thought of before. And
so this is an example of how
reinforcement learning can uh be a tool
to discover new solutions. And this
might be useful beyond games. But if we
want to for example discover uh curious
diseases or discover um things that
require experimentation, it provides a
tool for doing those tendencies.
Um and it's not just robots and games.
So nearly all modern language models use
some form of RL for post training. Uh
especially for more advanced reasoning
as well.
Uh there's also research on traffic
control using reinforcement learning and
finding ways to insert cars into um into
human driven cars in order to increase
the throughput on different roads.
Research on training generative models
with reinforcement learning. Uh in this
case for example trying to make the the
generations adhere to a particular
prompt. So uh what these are showing is
on the left if you ask uh the base
generative model to make a picture of a
dolphin riding a bike it'll give you
this which is not a very good picture
and then you can optimize with
reinforcement learning to get a picture
that uh is actually following the prompt
more effectively and likewise for other
prompts as well.
Uh and this also is um is being used for
chip design. Uh this is a paper that uh
uh designed chips that are used in
Google's production TPU uh which is also
pretty useful. Uh yeah,
great. Um so those are a few examples.
There's a number of others that I didn't
cover as well. Um the next thing that I
mentioned in terms of studying DRL is it
kind of seems somewhat fundamental to
intelligence. And for this I want to
tell a little bit of a story uh which is
that when I was starting my PhD uh right
after I graduated undergrad I joined a
lab that was uh looking at reinforcement
learning for robots and uh right next to
where I was I was sitting was this robot
here and oftentimes uh there was a
postto in the lab who was running
experiments with reinforcement learning
and so I would look over at the robot
and it would be doing things like this
and the thing that really kind of
fascinated ated me about watching this
robot is you could actually see it
learning uh over time and at the
beginning it knew nothing about how to
for example insert and kind of assemble
these two parts of a toy airplane and at
the end it's actually able to do it
quite performantly.
So this is like really really cool. You
can actually see it learning from its
own experience in the real world. Um so
essentially reinforcement learning
enables this kind of ability to get
better with practice that isn't uh
present in other machine learning
systems.
Now there was one caveat to this which
was that this particular robot had its
eyes closed. It uh it wasn't using a
camera essentially uh and that seemed
like a really fundamental limitation to
me. And so uh I actually kind of then
worked with the posttock on a follow-up
project uh with vision uh with with
cameras um and was able to in this case
then learn in the real world how to
insert the red block into the shape
sorting cube and again here with
experience is able to get better and
better uh as it practices the task over
and over again
>> and then after the learning process uh
it's still learning still improving it
ends up getting a success rate I think
around 95 or 100% success at the end.
Um, and then I can hold the block out uh
or at least a young version of me can
hold the block out for the robot and uh
the robot can then put it uh put the red
block into the sink for
now. These are very simple tasks. Uh
this was uh in some ways a long time
ago. Uh and now we have robots that can
fold laundry and and uh do dancing and
so forth.
Um,
but it's kind of one of the reasons why
I like showing these videos is they
really show the reinforcement learning
process in the real world and the
ability to improve with practice.
Um, at the same time, there's also a ton
of exciting research problems that are
open. Uh, and so if you're someone who's
excited about doing research, um,
there's challenges like how does uh,
this robot learn to represent what is
good for the task?
Um, or how does an agent generalize it
behavior not just to one scenario but to
many different scenarios? And um can we
apply such a system at scale with large
diverse data sets and transfer from
other tasks and other goals? Uh and can
we use reinforcement learning to learn
long horizon paths like cooking a meal
or solving a really hard math problem?
Um or and can robots practice fully
autonomously? And for this last point, I
showed you some videos of reinforcement
learning. That's not actually always
what it looks like. So sometimes if you
run reinforcement learning on robot it
looks more like this where the robot is
trying to hit the hockey puck into the
goal and every time the robot attempts
the task uh it then kind of needs to
start over and reattempt it and the
robot doesn't actually know how to undo
the task. And this is my friend Yvan. Um
you might notice that Yvan is actually
doing more work than what the robot is
doing which doesn't kind of quite seem
like the right way uh of doing things
and it's not practical to collect a lot
of data this way. Okay. So um and along
all these topics these are uh some of
the topics that we'll be covering in
this course as well. So we'll be talking
about reward learning and how to
represent different rewards. We'll be
talking about offline RL multitask RL
and metaarl hierarchy and reasoning um
and reset free RL as well.
Cool. Um so any questions on why deep RL
is interesting to study? Yeah. So in the
the question was uh how do you learn a
reward when the robot is learning in the
real world and in that particular
example the um we represented the reward
as the distance between or the negative
distance between the kind of the
position of the object and the goal
position of the object. And uh you might
have noticed that in the case with the
shape cube the robot was actually
holding the cube. Uh and so that could
that meant that we could actually
measure using the robot arm position
where the cube was as well. Um, now you
can't do this in practice in many
scenarios. Uh, it's kind of specific to
that task. Uh, and in the in the hockey
example, there there was actually a a
mocap marker on the hockey puck that
measured where it is in um yeah, where
it is in the room. And in general, it's
very hard. And that's why reward
learning uh is kind of necessary in
order to solve the problem in a more
general way.
Good question.
Okay. So now let's dive into modeling
behavior and uh and reinforce the
learning.
So
we need to figure out how to represent
experience as data. So like as the robot
was practicing, we need to think about
how we could actually represent what was
captured in that video as data to learn
from. Uh and so uh here's another
example of a robot learning in the real
world. Um we might also want to think
about how to represent text from like a
chatbot for example. we need to in
either of these cases we need to think
about experience that the agent collect
how do we actually write that down as
data.
So the way that we do that um typically
in reinforcement learning is first we'll
think about the state of the world and
we'll use s to denote the current state
of the world.
Um
and for example in in the case of the
robot the state of the world might be uh
like the position of the arm and the
position of the towel and the position
of the hook. uh or if you don't have
access to uh information about the towel
directly, it might just be an image
captured uh from the robot's camera and
the position of the joints of the arm if
you have access to that.
Now you can't always represent like you
can't always have access direct access
to the state of the world and so
sometimes we'll use uh we sometimes
we'll refer to an observation O uh and
use observations instead of states and
the difference between observations and
states is that with observations it may
not capture all of the information you
need to make a decision and you might
actually need to think about past
observations that you've seen before.
So, for example, for a chatbot, uh if
you're interacting with it, uh you could
think of the observation at a given time
step as the most recent message that you
sent to that chatbot.
And then, uh that most recent message
doesn't tell the chatbot everything it
needs to know about what the next
response should be. And so, what you
need is you actually need to give it the
history of past observations, uh not
just the current observation in order to
make a decision. And we'll we'll talk a
little bit more about this state
observation. uh distinction in a couple
slides.
So this is kind of capturing what the
agent is observing. Now we also need to
capture how it's taking actions, how
it's actually making decisions. And
we'll refer to those uh decisions as
actions. And we'll use the the letter A
to denote actions.
And then in terms of a given interaction
with the environment, we will think of
that as a trajectory. So that will be a
sequence of states and actions or a
sequence of observations and actions.
This is kind of uh one way to represent
behavior and this will then kind of
result in a data set of trajectories
rather than a data set of X5 pairs.
And then we need to think about like
what is actually the goal of the task.
Um and that's where reward functions
come in. And reward functions are
essentially telling us how good is a
given state in action.
In many cases, the reward function will
only depend on the state. Uh and for
example, it'll might tell you how close
is the towel to being hung or is the
towel hung or not. Um or in the case of
a tapot, it might be like how happy is
the user or did they give me a thumbs up
or a thumbs down?
And then this experience is um is is
kind of the trajectory. Um and that
trajectory might be augmented with the
rewards.
So this is kind of each time you uh kind
of roll out the policy uh you'll get
some sort of data in this form.
Let's talk a little bit more about
states and observations first. So um the
way that we'll we can then think about
states and actions is uh it's always a
lot like a markoff chain. So we'll have
um say we'll have the first state of the
world. This is for example in the robot
case. Let's say the towel is on the
table and there's a hook and the goal is
to put the towel on the hook. Um this
first state is like the robot in some
neutral position and the towel on the
table
and then the robot will take some
action. This is like moving its arm to a
particular location and that action and
the current state will inform what the
next state is.
And then from there uh the towel will be
maybe the towel was in the same position
if the robot was just moving in free
space or maybe the towel has moved. Uh
and then the robot will then take
another action. it will move its arm
again
and the
states and actions will then inform the
next state.
Now one crucial thing here is that the
um we kind of can think of how the
environment is changing under what's
called a dynamics function. So you have
like P of S3 given S2 and A2. This is
kind of the dynamics of the world. This
is how does the arm actually move in
space and how does the towel move in
space as a function of where it was
before and what the robot did.
And the crucial thing to notice here is
that S3 only depends on S2 and A2 and it
doesn't depend on S1.
And so like there's no S1 in this
probability distribution.
And essentially uh S3 is going to be um
independent of S1 if you condition on
S2.
And this sort of independence property
is called the Markov property.
Uh and it's uh one of the things that
actually ends up being very useful in
reinforcement learning. that allows you
to break up the problem in um into these
scenarios where you don't have to worry
about all the dependencies that come
before it.
Now, um if you have observations instead
of states, then things look a little bit
different. Uh and the way that we can
think about observations is the
observation is a function
of this current state and it may not
contain all the information that's in
the state. And so um the observation at
any given point in time for completeness
will draw each of them here.
And then if you don't have access if you
can't observe the states that means now
that O2 or sorry O3 um it's not just a
function of O2 and A2 it's actually also
a function of 01 if you cannot observe
the state.
Cool. So on the slides we can think
about uh this model where we have these
dynamics. We don't know how the world is
going to evolve. We can't directly
observe like how the power we can't
predict the future. Um and so these
dynamics are unknown and these dynamics
are independent of ST minus one in this
case and that's known as the markoff
property.
Any questions on that? Yeah. So the
question is in practice how many path
observations do we need to infer the
state? Uh it is heavily domain
dependent. Uh the
uh in like uh yeah heavily domain
dependent. In a lot of robotics examples
you can often get away with just using
like uh the current sensor observations.
Um but it depends a lot on like what the
sensors are. Like if you have tactile
sensors for example those are um
oftentimes don't contain as much
information as like vision observation
for example. And so like how close you
are to a table, you you have no idea
when you're not making contact. And then
once you make contact, you know. So
that's a lot more partially observable
than um than an image for example. But
then if you have the images in addition
to that, then that gives you a more
complete representation.
Yeah. So why is the reward function a
function of both the state and the
action and not just the state? Um one
example of this is uh we can go back to
a robotics example. So say that you are
a humanoid robot and you're trying to
learn how to walk. Um and maybe like one
natural reward function is just how much
forward progress have you made. So where
is your body and that would be kind of
dependent on the state. Um, one scenario
where you might want the action is is
that scenario where if you don't want to
be using too much energy uh because you
uh you don't want to be like uh tensing
up all the motors for example or I guess
pens up muscles more make more sense but
if you don't want to be exerting too
much pushing too much energy into your
motors uh then you'll want to depend on
the actions as well and you could
basically have some penalty on how much
torque you're putting through the
motors. Um so that's one example. Uh in
many cases you can just depend on the
state. uh but um there are some examples
where you don't you want to kind of
penalize taking too much action. Yeah.
So the question is um if the observation
is only part of the state then why does
um why does kind of a future observation
not independent of past observations and
um the reason for that is that the we
can actually go back to the tactile
example. So say that you are you make
contact and then you stop making contact
and then you make contact again. um the
in that case the most immediate past
observation doesn't actually tell you
that much information about the current
state uh and whereas this observation
actually tells you a lot more
information about the state and so the
um then 03 uh you actually can learn
more about you can actually figure out
more about 03 when you don't just
condition on O2 but also condition on
01.
Um, and there's also a way uh for folks
familiar with graphical models to
actually um think about if you kind of
marginalize out these variables, uh,
you'll actually see that in the
graphical model. Um, I don't want to go
into that today. Uh, but that's another
way that you can see this. Correct.
Yeah. Yeah. So, yeah, if you were to
estimate and predict 03, then you would
want you would need to use all of um,
you need to use past observations. Um
but the actual observation uh in this
graphical model is um kind of dependent
on the the state which might be
unobserved or unknown.
>> Cool. Um so let's walk through a couple
examples of what this might look like.
So uh in the robotics case the state
could be uh could include three
different things. One would be the RGB
images from any cameras on the robot,
the positions of all the joints of the
robot and the velocities of the joints.
Um, and so this is like kind of a fairly
common state representation for a robot
system. And the like the images would be
like uh would be actually a different
dimensionality than the positions. And
so you might need to actually configure
your neural network in a way that can
accept those different dimensionalities.
The action would then be the commanded
next joint position. So how are you
going to kind of move your joint? If
your joint's currently like at 90
degrees, maybe you'll try to move it to
92 degrees.
The trajectory then would be a sequence
of states and actions. So a sequence of
videos or sequence of of images which is
essentially a video, a sequence of joint
positions and a sequence of command and
joint positions.
Now what does that sequence actually
entail? Uh typically what we do is we'll
discretize time and this sequence will
then for example be at 20 hertz. So
you'll your video will be 20 frames per
second and you'll have joint
observations 20 times per second and
you'll also have commanded actions 20
times per second. Uh I always found this
a little bit unintuitive when I first
learned it because as a person I'm I
don't really think about like making a
decision 20 times every second. Uh but
it is often times the most practical way
to uh represent data and behavior on
like physical systems like robots.
Uh, and then for the reward function,
there's a few things you could use here.
One could be one if the towel is on the
hook uh in in state s and zero
otherwise. You could also have some sort
of penalty on on like the torques that
you're applying on the action or
something like that.
So that's a robot example. Now let's go
to like a chatbot example. So here the
observation we we we would likely
wouldn't have like a compact state
representation and so we be using
observations and the observation could
be the user's most recent message.
The action would be the chatbot's next
message. So this would be potentially a
sentence or a paragraph. It potentially
could actually be very large.
>> And then you could think of the
trajectory as the conversation trace. So
like the kind of history of the current
conversations
and unlike in the robotics example, this
won't necessarily be at like a fixed
like 20 hertz frequency. Uh it might
take longer for a user to respond or
something like that. And so this is an
example of how trajectories might vary
in terms of how time is represented. So
in the first case, time is represented
as a 20th of a second, whereas in the
second case, time is represented as when
the user responds next.
Um, and then as an example reward, maybe
it's one if the user gives an upvote,
negative 10 if the user gives a down
vote, uh, and zero if there's no user
feedback.
Okay, so here's an these are examples of
how we can set up reinforcement
learning. Now, I would like to ask you
to formulate uh a reinforcement learning
problem. And in particular, uh,
I'd like you to define the state or
observation, the action, trajectory, and
reward for either one of these three
examples or choose your own example.
Yeah. So in this example, um the there's
a question of basically question is like
why would this be an observation versus
a state? Um it could actually be
formulated both ways potentially. Uh the
it kind of depends on the details of the
sensor measurement. So, um, as one
example, if your sensors are just
looking at like current, like a LAR of
like the current depth around you and
like a picture of what's in front of
you, um, yeah, maybe something along
those lines. Uh, one thing that that
would be missing is like how fast the
cars are moving around you, uh, like the
velocity of the cars. And that, um,
that's probably quite important for, uh,
like what's going to happen in the
future, uh, like if it's stopped versus
moving at 60 m hour. Um, now you could
potentially try to include uh a history
of like LAR information to get that
velocity information and then represent
your state as like a three kind of a 3se
secondond history or for example. Um,
and this will kind of represent a theme
which is that typically to represent uh
to handle observations will use a little
bit of history and then that can form
your state representation. Um, so it's a
little bit ambiguous in this particular
case and yeah it comes down to the
details. Yeah. Yeah. So the question is
in the robot example, if the reward is
one if it's on the hang on the hook and
zero otherwise, how do you actually
learn? Because you if you're just like
if you don't actually ever do that at
any point, then you'll have very little
supervision signal. You'll just have
zero reward all the time. Uh and so in
that actually in that particular video
we initialized um we actually showed the
robot how to do it uh a couple times as
initialization and that helped uh helped
it with what we'll call exploration. Um
and if you have very sparse rewards
rewards that have very uh little signal
and are not kind of nicely shaped
towards the goal then usually that that
kind of data might be important for uh
for jump starting the reinforcement
learning process. Cool. Cool. Yeah. So,
um, if folks couldn't hear that, the
you'd have the state being, um,
something like the HTML and like the
URL, like information about the web page
and where you're at. The action would be
interacting with it. Uh, and the reward
would be like whether or not some task
was completed. Yeah. So, the question
is, is basically everything an
observation because sensors are like may
not be perfect. Um, so you could always
choose to model something as an
observation if you're worried about like
sensor noise or something like that. Um
there are large in some ways potentially
like large downsides to it if you need
to add a lot of history. Um the and so
sometimes we will kind of approximately
um approximate something as the state
even if it might be blocking information
like maybe um I don't know once every
like 10,000 times the sensor fails uh
and gives you like a black image or
something like that. um even though that
would technically be um like an
observation case, you might still use it
as a state representation because of how
it affects the algorithms.
>> Yeah. So, if I understand correctly,
you're asking for observations, it could
either be like everything currently or
it could be a delta from the previous
observation. Um yeah, and the yeah, it
would come out down to different
trade-offs. oftent times um if you are
going to be including a lot of history
then uh kind of compressing it by using
deltas uh could potentially make a lot
of sense um but it once we get into
policies um maybe it'll also become more
clear okay so now that we've talked
about formulating the reinforcement
learning problem let's talk about
actually representing behavior so we
want to map typically from states or
observations to action and we will to do
that we'll use what's called a policy
Um, and this policy will often use pi to
denote a policy or basically almost
always use pi. Um, and this can just be
a neural network. In this case, it's a
convolutional neural network. It could
be a transformer. It could be like a
simple fully connected neural network.
Uh, it could be a linear function. Um,
and this is going to be mapping from the
states or observations or the sequence
of observations to actions. um we'll use
typically theta to refer to the
parameters of that neural network that
you're trying to learn.
And so then when you're actually using a
policy to take actions, we'll then
observe a state uh take an action uh and
observe a next state. And when we take
actions, we're actually going to be
sampling from our neural network. Uh so
we'll actually be running a forward pass
to the neural network uh to select an
action and then execute that action in
the real world and observe the next
state.
Um,
cool. Uh, and so the result of this
process is a trajectory. And when we're
using a policy to generate this
trajectory, we often refer to it as a
roll out or an episode. Um, you can
think of it as like kind of one episode
of learning, one episode of learning is
like at one attempt and then trying it
again and again. And I guess the
terminology roll out is in the sense
that you're um you're kind of
sequentially uh going policy dynamics,
policy dynamics. since you're kind of
rolling out this process to create a
trajectory.
Um, great. And then if you only have
observations and you don't have states,
the solution is to give your policy
memory. And so you can pass in multiple
observations. Whereas if you only give
it a state, you actually don't have to
give it any memory and you can just give
it as input state. Uh this is very
convenient because uh if you have a
large amount of um memory it will take
up a large memory on your computer or uh
on your GPU. Uh but if you only have
observations then you have uh in some
ways no choice but to provide that
memory to the policy and for this you
may use like sequence models for example
in language models you're going to be
using sequence models that use the
previous observations.
Yeah. So the question is is t like the
current time step or is it kind of
general from the beginning to the end?
So um this capital t I'm using to denote
kind of the end of the trajectory. So
the length the number of states and
actions in a trajectory. Um and then t
I'm kind of referring to a given time
step. Um and this uh and kind of
generalizing it so that you can think
about this as happening at all time
steps from t equals from lowercase t
equals 1 to lowerase t equals capital t.
Is it ever useful to condition it on the
both the observation and the state? So
in this case um the state has strictly
more information than the current
observation and so uh it isn't useful to
add the observation if the state is
truly the state that captures
everything.
So if we go back to this diagram if we
um if we have states then we only need
to provide the current state whereas if
we have observations that's where adding
history is helpful. So it's it's a
distinction between states and
observations.
Why is it having history of observation
football? Yeah.
Yeah. So basically the past observations
will help give you more information
about what F1 is. Uh and so if you only
have observations and you don't know
what the underlying state of the world
is. So we can as another example in like
language modeling um if you are having a
conversation with a user um each thing
that the user says is a different
observation and the past observations
will actually tell you a lot about what
the current state of the world is. So if
their first question was like can you
write this piece of code to me and then
you maybe wrote some piece of code and
they give you some feedback. It's
actually very important to include all
those past observations um to actually
capture the the full state of the world.
I mean that might not be true in all
cases. Uh the but in in like yeah many
many cases the previous observations uh
will also be useful for the current
state.
>> Yeah. So you there also could be
scenarios where you might want kind of a
two-stage process. One where you first
infer the state and then a second
process where you um where you then
predict the action from that state. If
you have some idea for like a good
representation for the underlying state,
then that sort of information could be
useful in trying to model the underlying
state. Um in other cases, uh it's
simplest just to go straight from
observation stack.
Okay. Um moving on a little bit. So
we've talked about states, actions,
policies. What is actually the goal of
reinforcement learning? Uh so our goal
is to maximize reward. And so if we have
a trajectory um we don't want to just
optimize for like the reward at one time
step but we want to optimize for having
reward across the entire trajectory
and so we can represent this as
maximizing the sum of rewards.
Now one thing that came up is that this
is actually not a deterministic
quantity. So if you have a policy
um and you're then executing that policy
in the world,
the reward that you get isn't always
going to be the same every time you run
your policy.
Uh and so a question for you, uh why is
this not a deterministic quantity? And
what are the sources of variability that
might cause the sum of rewards to differ
from one trajectory to another
trajectory?
Yeah. Yeah. So, one source of
variability is that the the state
doesn't just depend on the act uh the
action in the state, but there's also
kind of some randomness that can affect
the next state. Other sources of
variabilities. Yeah. So, your policy may
not be deterministic either. So, there's
kind of two really key sources. There's
a good question. You might have a
stoastic reward function. So, typically
we actually model the reward. There's a
very interesting point. We often
typically model it as deterministic as a
function. um the and and kind of have
the source of randomness come from
states and actions. Now um if you don't
know the state then it could actually be
viewed as stoastic if you only have the
observations
right so if you're doing reward learning
um is there the question is is there
stoasticity there um typically you'll
still model it as a as a reward function
well so you might have some you might
not have full certainty over exactly
what the reward is um and perhaps you
might want to leverage that uncertainty
into like in some ways in the learning
process Um that's uh maybe something to
take offline. There's some
considerations there. Yeah. So the other
thing is your goals might change over
time. Um and in that case the reward
function will change. Well actually
often model that as a different a whole
different decision process at that point
if the rewards change um rather than
kind of having it being with within the
same one. Um the yeah there are
scenarios where you might want a
non-stationary
decision process I guess but um and you
can actually often put that randomness
into the state instead of putting it in
the reward function like maybe there's
some underlying goal that you can't
observe that's in the state uh and then
the reward function remains
deterministic. Um and so yeah generally
without losing generality you can push
that into the state if needed.
Cool. So um the two main sources of
variability that you have to worry about
are the world is stoastic. So the
environment this these dynamic this is
this is a distribution it's not a
deterministic function and the second is
that the policy is also not um not
deterministic. And so in driving for
example other cars are going to behave
in ways that are random and your car
might not make the same decision every
time.
Cool.
Um, and so if we can if we actually want
to think about maximizing rewards,
we can then add in the policy into this
diagram where there's essentially if if
you have access to state, there would be
an error from here to here that is
modeling
this distribution and likewise from here
to here.
Now if we then wanted to actually write
down
what rewards look like, we need to think
about a probability distribution over
trajectories. We actually need to think
about like what is um yeah what is
actually the kind of distribution over
um over futures that we'll see. The way
that we can think about that is we'll
have some initial state. Uh there may
actually also be randomness here that we
haven't talked about like the initial
conditions of the world might change and
if you're like playing a game for
example like how the cards are dealt out
will vary and then after the state there
is um you're going to be making a
decision with your policy
and then once you make that decision
there is randomness that arises from
the
um from the dynamic and then And we if
we want to think about the probability
of a given trajectory, it's going to be
the probability of the first state, then
the probability of taking the next
action, then the probability of taking
the next um observing the next state,
then the probability of taking the
action after that, and then the next
state, and so on. And so then we can
think about the probability
of a given trajectory as being
the initial state probability plus the
product of the probabilities from the
policy and the dynamic where uh here t=
1 to capital t.
And then once we formulate this
probability distribution over
trajectories, then we can think about
maximizing reward as actually maximizing
our expected rewards under this
probability distribution.
So
we'll kind of think about the
expectation of trajectories sampled from
this distribution
of the sum of like state and actions in
this trajectory of
the reward of that statement.
Um, and then this is our goal. Our goal
is to maximize this. And our goal is to
find a policy pi that maximizes
the expected sum of awards.
And so that is written
right here.
Now note that unlike in supervised
learning we um this doesn't look like
something that you can like very like
well pi actually doesn't even appear in
this equation but the way that it comes
in is how it's affecting the
trajectories. So this distribution of
trajectories is a function of pi right
here and you actually want to find the
the the the policy that will lead to the
highest award.
uh and a lot of this class will be
figuring out how do we actually optimize
behavior um under this particular
objective. Yeah. The question is does
capital T have to be fixed? Uh it does
not have to be fixed. It can be
variable. Um it's a little bit easier to
write down if it's fixed. Uh but um
yeah, you can also think about it as
like um like basically the the length of
the expresses.
Yeah. So, one other topic that will come
up in depth a lot more is um when you
think about rewards, this is weighting
the rewards over the entire trajectory
equally. And it's saying that you care
about immediate reward just as much as
you care about future rewards. And in
some cases, you might care about
immediate reward more than future reward
reward. So, for example, if this t is
like a thousand years, uh maybe you
don't care so much about your rewards a
thousand years from now than you care
about your rewards today. Uh and so
another way that you could actually
formulate the reinforcement learning
objective is not just this kind of
vanilla sum of rewards, but you could
actually weight your rewards by what's
called a discount factor, where that
discount factor um actually depends on
key. So you actually uh one of the ways
we often do that is adding a discount
factor that's raised to the power of t.
Um and this means that if a discount
factor usually this is some value that's
kind of uh
greater than zero and less than or equal
to one. If this is one, it's the same as
the original formulation. Um and as you
make it lower and lower, you're being
more greedy. you're caring a lot more
about uh near-term rewards than about
far rewards. Um yeah, we'll talk a
little bit more about discount factors
in uh in a couple lectures.
>> Cool. Um as an aside, uh we've talked
about how our policy is a distribution
and so it's it's not deterministic, it's
stochastic. Why might we want to do
that? There's a couple reasons why we
might want our policy to not be
deterministic.
The first is that um if you want to
learn, you probably have to try
different things. Like if you're
learning how to play tennis, you
probably shouldn't try the same exact
technique over and over again. You need
to actually explore and uh and and try
different strategies in order to do it.
And so that can be represented as a
stoastic policy that's trying a few
different strategies and trying to
figure out which strategy is best.
Um and then another case is there's
scenarios where you collect data from
people uh or from different systems and
those people are taking different
strategies. And if you want to model the
way that they're approaching a problem,
you may need your policy to be stoastic
as well.
Okay. Um and for this we can also
leverage tool from generative models
where you're actually thinking about um
not just a neural network that maps from
A to B but actually a generative model
over actions given states and
observations.
I think this is the last thing we'll
touch on and introduce which is how do
we decide how good well okay second to
last thing um how do we decide how good
a policy is? Uh, and this is really
useful to think about because if you
don't know how good your policy is, then
you're not going to be able to make your
policy better.
And the terminology that we use to think
about this is referred to as a value
function. So we often think about the
value function for a policy of a given
state and we denote it uh typically as
vi of f. And essentially what this means
is it's the future expected reward if
you start at S and then follow pi from
then onward. Um and so it's basically
this equation except starting at S under
um under your current policy.
Um the and similarly to this another um
thing that we'll start talking about not
in Friday's lecture but starting next
week is cube value functions as well.
And this is very similar to the value
function, but instead of starting at S,
you're you're actually starting from S,
then taking action A, and then following
pi, where action A might be different
from what policy pi might have taken.
I'm not going to go into depth on what
these two functions are today, but I
wanted to introduce them because we'll
be using them quite a lot. Um and so
it's good to start wrapping your head
around what they are. Uh and as we start
to use them more in future lectures.
Okay. And then the types of algorithms
we'll cover uh the idea behind imitation
learning is to mimic a policy that
achieves high reward. We'll then next
week start talking about policy
gradients that try to directly
differentiate this objective and
actually learn from from practice and
experience.
From there we'll talk about actor critic
algorithms that estimate the value of
the current policy and use it that to
make the policy better.
We'll talk about value based methods
that try to estimate the value of the
optimal policy and then use that to back
out a good policy. And then lastly we'll
talk about model based methods that
actually learn how to model the dynamics
of the world like try to predict the
future and then use that to improve the
policy or for planning.
Now you might be wondering why do we
have so many different algorithms for
optimizing this objective? In supervised
learning, we like just have gradient
descent. It works. It's great. It's
simple. Um in reinforcement learning,
things are less simple. Uh algorithms
make different trade-offs and thrive
under different assumptions. Uh and so
it's going to depend on, for example,
how easy or cheap is it to collect data.
And if you're in a simulator, for
example, it's really really cheap to
collect lots of data versus if you're
handwriting um kind of uh kind of
responses or handwriting um like
actually interacting with a person
that's writing things that's going to be
more expensive.
Um also, how cheap and and easy are
different forms of supervision? Do you
have demonstrations? Do you have
detailed rewards? Um how important is
stability and ease of use versus data
efficiency? uh maybe you have more time
to uh to kind of change some of the
hyperparameters if it doesn't need
massive amounts of data.
Uh there's also some considerations with
regard to what your actions look like.
How high dimensional are they? Are they
continuous or discreet? Uh is it easy to
learn the dynamics model. Um so yeah,
these are these are some of the reasons
why we have a lot of different
algorithms and we'll be talking about
different algorithms and and where
they're applied uh in the later parts of
this course.
Okay, so to recap, um there's a lot of
terminology and a lot of notation in
reinforcement learning and um wanted to
start introducing them today because
we'll be starting to use them quite a
bit in the following lectures. So we
talked about states, we talked about
observations, we talked about actions,
reward functions, and also initial state
distribution and dynamics. These form
what's called a Markov decision process.
Uh or if you only have observations,
it's called a partially observed Markov
decision process. uh or an MDP or a POM
DP. I didn't want to bring in this
notation until the very end because it
uh doesn't actually really matter what
it's called uh but it's useful in the
long term if people are referring to
MDPs. Now you know what they're
referring to. They're referring to this
formulation of a reinforcement learning
problem.
Um and then we also talked about
trajectories, policies, the objective of
reinforcement learning, value functions
and and Q functions briefly.